Roy Doty Cartoons
Roy Doty Cartoons
1947-1970
Doty, Roy, 1922-
12 linear ft.
Artwork of the American cartoonist and illustrator. Original book covers and illustrations, and cartoons for magazines and newspapers.
148947
Biographical History
Roy Doty (1922-2015) was an American cartoonist and illustrator, with a career spanning more than sixty years.
Doty grew up in Columbus, Ohio and served in World War II as a cartoonist. After the war he moved to New York City where he began his career as a freelance cartoonist. He wrote and drew the Laugh In strip for three years in the 1960s, and his Wordless Workshop, published in Family Handyman, has been running for more than 50 years. Doty illustrated more than 170 children's books, wrote 27, edited several monthly newsletters including a children's newsletter for the American Institute for Cancer Research, and was published in venues as diverse as the New York Times, Field & Stream, Popular Science, the London Daily Mail, and Elle Magazine. Doty's artwork has appeared on packages, book covers, and advertising; his clients included Black and Decker, Buick, the Copper Council, Ford, Macy's, Minute Maid, Mobil Oil, Perrier, Safari Club International, and Texas Instruments.
Doty was recognized numerous times by his peers, including a six-time recipient of The National Cartoonists Society's award for Advertising Illustration (1967, 1970, 1978, 1989, 1996, 2005). He also received an award for illustration of greeting cards from the National Cartoonists Society in 1994.
Dory died in March 18, 2015, age 92.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Roy Doty Cartoons collection consists of original artwork and some published drawings.
The Original artwork series comprises the bulk of the collection. The series is subdivided into the following: book illustrations, magazine cartoons and newspaper cartoons. Book illustrations are arranged alphabetically by book title and some also include cover art. Th illustrated titles in the collection include: Instant Dog: The Quick and Easy Way to Produce a Family Dog, Elinor Goulding Smith's The Complete Book of Absolutely Perfect Baby and Child Care, Letters to Paul Baby, with a letter concerning Paul Baby illustrations and more.
The subseries magazine cartoons contains original artwork from several publications, including: Charm, Golf, Look, The New Republic, Woman's Day, Woman's Home Companion, Ski magazine as well as others. The series also has original art from Family Circle and Family Weekly, including illustrations for Family Weekly poetry. Miscellaneous art in this series contains art for Macy's advertisements and other unidentified cartoons featured in magazines.
Newspaper cartoons, another subseries, includes original daily and Sunday panels from the comic strip Laugh In (1968-1970) and over 500 original cartoons from The New York Times (1948-1966).
Printed material consists of one item for The Compleat Dissenter, an United clipping from The Christian Herald and miscellaneous artwork. The miscellaneous art includes cartoon proofs and a printed illustration, most likely from The Herald Tribune's Today's Living and Look magazine.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged by series. Similar material is often not housed together due to size. At times, items were left in their original order, such as many of the book illustrations, as opposed to being organized in alphabetical or chronological order.
Related Material
The book Instant Dog: The Quick and Easy Way to Produce a Family Dog featuring illustrations by Roy Doty was removed from the collection and transferred to Rare Books.
has collections of more than 150 cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Art -- Illustrators; Doty, Roy, 1922-; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Illustration of books.; Illustrators -- United States.; Cartoons (humorous images); Illustrations.; Cartoonists.; Illustrators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Roy Doty, 1967-1971.
Inventory
- Original artwork
  - Book illustrations
    - The Battered Bride: Things Your Mother Never Told You, circa 1960; 37 items (Oversize  1)
    - The Complete Book of Absolutely Perfect Baby and Child Care, Elinor Goulding Smith, undated; 40 items (Box 1)
    - Exit Backwards, Bowing (McMillan Publishing Company), 1970; 25 panels (Box 1)
    - Instant Dog: The Quick and Easy Way to Produce a Family Dog (Dutton Publishing), circa 1968; 55 items (Oversize 5)
    - Is Europe Necessary?, Ronald M. Deutsch, circa 1960; 2 items (Oversize 1)
    - Letters to Paul Baby, Paul Dixon (World Publishing Company), 1970; 18 panels, 1 letter (Box 1)
    - A Man Around the House, Harlan Miller, (Random House), undated; 2 items (Oversize 6)
    - Tale of a Whistling Shrimp, Vladimir Grinioff, (Dutton Publishing), undated; 1 item (Oversize 6)
    - Three Cheers for Me, Donald Lamont Jack, undated; 1 item (Oversize 6)
    - The Unfair Sex: The Expose of the Human Male for Young Women of Most Ages, Nina Farewell, circa 1960; 55 items (Box 1)
  - Magazine cartoons
    - Charm, Jul 1951 - Jan 1955; undated; 10 items (Oversize 19)
    - Family Circle magazine
      - Mar 1950 - Dec 1959, 89 items (Oversize 13)
      - Jan 1960 - Jul 1966, 57 items (Oversize 12)
      - Undated, 62 items (Oversize 12)
      - Undated, 1 item (Oversize 19)
    - Family Weekly, undated; 9 items (Oversize 7)
    - Family Weekly, undated; 43 items (Oversize 4)
      Possibly Family Weekly poetry.
    - Family Weekly poetry, Jul 1964 - Jul 1965; undated
      - A-D, 13 items (Oversize 1)
        Address to my beagle
        All is forgiven
        Auto intoxication
        Be my Valedtide
        Beach togs
        Birds of a feather
        Cooks detour
        Cordon blooey
        Crossword puzzle for strikes back
        Cutting remarks
        Dad's lament
        Day after Christmas
        Dish count
      - E-G, 13 items (Oversize 1)
        East system
        Easter habit
        Effervescent adolescent
        Fall guy
        Father and son talk
        Father chooses a Christmas Tree
        Father cleans the basement
        Feast song
        Friends of the bride
        The gal in the galley
        Go, Mom, go
        Good clean fun
        The graduate
      - H-K, 11 items (Oversize 2)
        Hair brained
        Home grown tomatoes
        Hope springs eternal
        Hot items
        House call
        House detective
        I just let it roll off
        Inscription for a tool box
        It'll be a beauty
        It pays to be methodical
        King for a day
      - L-Mi, 10 items (Oversize 2)
        Lines inscribed with
        Lingering lineup
        Little lyric for Labor Day
        Lost and found dept.
        Loving dangerously
        Man power
        Maternal address system
        Meeting
        Milestone
        Minor league baseball schedule
      - Mo-O, 15 items (Oversize 2)
        Morning horoscope
        Music note
        My co-pilot is no pilot
        My man Saturday
        Near tragedy
        New Year's Resolutions -- phooey
        No carrying charge
        No hard feelings
        No tobacco road
        Nook knack
        Once in a lifetime
        One missing
        "Oops!"
        Out of the past
        Overwhelming popularity
      - P-Q, 11 items (Oversize 3)
        Parents also have growing pains
        Party of the first part
        Paternal vespers
        Phoney business
        Polishing up for the room
        Pop concert
        Premonition
        Price tags
        Putting in my five cents worth
        Quick switch
        Quiz for mothers
      - R-S, 14 items (Oversize 3)
        Relics retreat
        Remedies for a cold
        Saga of Billy Smith
        Sand in my crankcase
        Saturday chef
        The score on decor
        Semester song
        Social error
        Sockfull
        Spatter matters
        Step right up
        Story for Mother's Day
        Sylvan soliloquy
        Sylvester and Genevieve
      - T-W, 14 items (Oversize 3)
        Tenting on the old camp ground
        Thanks but I prefer less for my money
        They went thataway
        Three cheers
        Trapped
        The tree trimmer
        "Uniformity"
        The unkindest cut
        Unsettled with showers
        Vacation souvenirs
        Weekend weather brief
        Welcome July
        Well defined
        When she stands up straight I hardly recognize her
      - Family Weekly, Types of Drivers, undated; 5 items (Oversize 6)
        Compact
        Economy model
        Extended payment plan
        Mini-car
        Sports car
    - Golf magazine, undated; 1 item (Oversize 11)
    - Holiday magazine, Jun 1950 - Aug 1951; undated; 7 items (Oversize 1)
    - Look magazine, Apr 1958 - Jan 1962; undated; 28 items (Oversize 13)
    - The New Republic, Nov 7 1947; 1 item (Box 1)
    - Ski magazine, undated; 4 items (Oversize 13)
    - Sports Illustrated, Aug 1957 - Sep 1958; 7 items (Oversize 13)
    - Suburbia Today, Jun 1961 - Jul 1963; 4 items (Oversize 13)
    - Suburbia Today, undated; 6 items (Oversize 1)
    - This Week magazine, May 1950 - Aug 1954; undated; 15 items (Oversize 6)
    - Today's Living, The Herald Tribune Magazine, 1956-1958; 2 folders (Oversize 18)
    - Today's Living, The Herald Tribune Magazine, 1958; 1 large item (Oversize 19)
    - Today's Living, The Herald Tribune Magazine, 1959 - 1963; undated; 98 items (Oversize 14)
    - Vista Magazine, undated; 1 item (Oversize 18)
    - Woman's Day, Jun 1950; undated; 5 items (Oversize 18)
    - Woman's Home Companion, Oct 1950 - Mar 1951; 8 items (Oversize 11)
      How to Defrost a Freezer
      How to Stretch a Refrigerator
      Now We Have More Time for Fun
    - Miscellaneous
      - Macy's ads, undated; 3 items (Oversize 11)
      - Unidentified cartoons, undated; 8 items (Box 1)
  - Newspaper cartoons
    - Laugh In
      - Daily panels, Oct - Dec 1968; 61 items (Oversize 7)
      - Daily panels, Jan - Jun 1969; 108 items (Oversize 8)
      - Daily panels, Jul - Dec 1969; Jan - May 1970; 126 items and 80 items (Oversize 9)
      - Sunday panels, Nov 1968 - Mar 1970; 34 items (Oversize 10)
    - The New York Times
      - 1948 (Oversize  11)
      - 1948, 1 large item (Oversize  19)
      - 1949 (Oversize  17)
      - 1950 (Oversize  11)
      - 1951 (Oversize  17)
      - 1952 (Oversize  17)
      - 1953 (Oversize  11)
      - 1955-1956 (Oversize  17)
      - 1957-1958 (Oversize 11)
      - 1959 (Oversize 16)
      - 1959, 1 large item (Oversize  19)
      - 1960 (Oversize 18)
      - 1960, 1 large item (Oversize  19)
      - 1961 (Oversize 16)
      - 1962 (Oversize 16)
      - 1962 (Oversize 15)
      - 1963 (Oversize 15)
      - 1963 (Oversize 19)
      - 1964 (Box 1)
      - 1964 (Oversize 15)
      - 1964 (Oversize 20)
      - 1965 (Oversize 20)
      - 1966 (Oversize 18)
      - Undated (Oversize 18)
- Printed material
  - The Compleat Dissenter, 1 item (Box 1)
  - United clipping, The Christian Herald; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous art, proof sheets and illustration, possibly from Today's Living and Look magazine; 6 items (Box 1)